<body>
The <date>day</date> before my departure from <placeName>Padua</placeName>, I visited signor <persName>Tromba</persName>, <persName>Tartini</persName>'s <persName>scholar</persName> and <persName>successor</persName>.
He was so obliging as to play several of his <persName>master</persName>'s <music>solos</music>, particularly two which he had made just before his death, of which I begged a copy, regarding these last drops of his pen as sacred relics of so great and original a genius.
<placeName>VENICE</placeName>.
I had many enquiries to make, and had very sanguine expectations from this <placeName>city</placeName>, with regard to the music of past times as well as the present.
The <placeName><placeName>church</placeName> of <date>st</date></placeName>.
Marc has had a constant supply of able <persName>masters</persName>, from the time of <persName>Adriano</persName>, <persName>Zarlino</persName>'s <persName>predecessor</persName>, to <persName>Galuppi</persName>, its present worthy <persName>composer</persName>.
<placeName>Venice</placeName> has likewise been one of the first <placeName>cities</placeName> in <placeName>Europe</placeName> that has cultivated the musical drama or <music>cpera</music>: and, in the graver stile, it has been honoured with a <persName>Lotti</persName> and a <music>Mar138 Marcello</music>.
Add to these advantages the <placeName>conservatorios</placeName> established here, and the <music><persName>songs</persName> of the Gondolieri</music>, or <persName>Water-men</persName>, which are so celebrated, that every musical <persName>collector</persName> of taste in <placeName>Europe</placeName> is well furnished with them, and it will appear that my expectations were well grounded.
The first music I heard here was in the <placeName>street</placeName>, immediately on my arrival, performed by an <persName>itinerant <persName>band</persName></persName> of two <instrument>fiddles</instrument>, a <instrument>violoncello</instrument>, and a <instrument>voice</instrument>, who, though as unnoticed here as <persName>small-coalmen</persName> or <persName>oyster-women</persName> in <placeName>England</placeName>, performed so well, that in any other <placeName>country</placeName> of <placeName>Europe</placeName> they would not only have excited attention, but have acquired applause, which they justly merited.
These two <instrument>violins</instrument> played difficult passages very neatly, the <instrument>base</instrument> stopped well in tune, and the <instrument>voice</instrument>, which was a <persName>woman</persName>'s, was well toned, and had several essentials belonging to that of a good <persName>singer</persName>, such as compass, shake, and volubility; but I shall not mention all the performances of this kind 13 kind which I met with here; as they happened so frequently, the repetition would be tiresome.
This <placeName>city</placeName> is famous for its <placeName>conservatorios</placeName> or <placeName>musical <placeName>schools</placeName></placeName>, of which it has four, the <placeName>Ospidale della <placeName>Pietà</placeName></placeName>, the <placeName>Mendicanti</placeName>, the <placeName>Incurabile</placeName>, and the <placeName>Ospidalette a s.
Giovanni e Paulo</placeName>, at each of which there is a performance <date>every saturday</date> and <date>sunday <date>evening</date></date>, as well as on great <date>festivals</date>.
I went to that of the <placeName>Pietà</placeName>, the <date>evening</date> after my arrival, <date>saturday, August 4</date>.
The present <persName><instrument>Maestro</instrument> di Capella</persName> is signor <persName>Furlanetti</persName>, a <persName>priest</persName>, and the <persName>performers</persName>, both vocal and instrumental, are all <persName>girls</persName>; the <instrument>organ</instrument>, <instrument>violins</instrument>, <instrument>flutes</instrument>, <instrument>violoncellos</instrument>, and even <instrument>French <instrument>horns</instrument></instrument>, are supplied by these <persName>females</persName>.
It is a kind of <persName>Foundling Hospital</persName> for natural <persName>children</persName>, under the protection of several <persName>nobles</persName>, citizens, and <persName>merchants</persName>, who, though the revenue is very great, yet contribute annually to its support.
These <persName>girls</persName> are maintained here till they are married, married, and all those who have talents for music are taught by the best <persName>masters</persName> of <placeName>Italy</placeName>.
The composition and performance I heard <date>to-night</date> did not exceed mediocrity; among the <persName>singers</persName> I could discover no remarkable fine <instrument>voice</instrument>, or <persName>performer</persName> possessed of great taste.
However, the instruments finished with a <music>symphony</music>, the first movement of which, in point of spirit, was well written and executed.
On <date>sunday <date>morning</date>, August 5</date>, I went to the <placeName>Greek <placeName>church</placeName></placeName>, which has been tolerated here ever since the time of <persName>Leo</persName> X The <date>service</date> is performed in the Greek language; the <music>epistles</music> and <music>gospels</music> are chanted by a <persName>high-<persName>priest</persName></persName> in a <placeName>pulpit</placeName>, and the <music>prayers</music> and <music>responses</music> are sung in a kind of melody totally different from any other I had ever heard in or out of the <placeName>church</placeName>.
In this there is no <instrument>organ</instrument>, but it is more crowded with ornaments, and its ceremonials are more numerous than in any of the Romish <placeName>churches</placeName>.
From I From thence I went to <date>st</date>.
Marc’s, and heard a <music>mass</music> in music, which was sunby the <persName>priests</persName>, accompanied by the <instrument>organ</instrument> only, much in the manner of our full <music>anthems</music>.
At <date>st</date>.
<placeName>Luke's <placeName>church</placeName></placeName> I l'kewise heard part of a <music>mass</music> with instruments; some of the tenor <instrument>voices</instrument> here were good, and the <music>airs</music> written and sung with taste; the music was composed by a <persName>priest</persName>.
There was an excellent <music>fugue</music> in the last <music>chorus</music>, well worked and well performed.
In the <date>afternoon</date> of the same <date>day</date> I went to the <placeName><placeName>hospital</placeName> de <placeName>Mendicanti</placeName></placeName>, for <persName>orphan <persName>girls</persName></persName>, who are taught to sing and play, and on <date>sundays</date> and <date>festivals</date> they sing <music>divine <date>service</date></music> in <music>chorus</music>.
<persName>signor <persName>Bertoni</persName></persName> is the present <persName><instrument>Maestro</instrument> di Capella</persName>.
There was a <music>hymn</music> performed with <music>solos</music> and <music>chorusses</music>, and a <music>mottetto à voce sola</music>, which last was very well performed, particularlyan accompanied <music>recitative</music>, which was pronounced with great force and energy.
Upon the whole, the compositions had some pretty passages, mixed with with others that were not very new.
The <persName>subjects</persName> of the <music>fugues</music> and <music>chorusses</music> were trite, and but slightly put together.
The <persName>girls</persName> here I thought accompanied the <instrument>voices</instrument> better than at the <placeName>Pietà</placeName>: as the <music>chorusses</music> are wholly made up of female <instrument>voices</instrument>, they are never in more than three parts, often only in two; but these, when reinforced by the instruments, have such an effect, that the full complement to the <instrument>chords</instrument> is not missed, and the melody is much more sensible and marked, by being less charged with harmony.
In these <placeName>hospitals</placeName> many of the <persName>girls</persName> sing in the counter tenor as low as A and <music>G</music>, which enables them always to keep below the <instrument>soprano</instrument> and mezzo <instrument>soprano</instrument>, to which they sing the <instrument>base</instrument>; and this seems to have been long practised in <placeName>Italy</placeName>, as may be seen in the examples of composition given in the old <persName>writers</persName>, such as <persName>Zarlino</persName>, <persName>Glariano</persName>, <persName>Kircher</persName>, and others, where the lowest part of three is often written in the <instrument>counter-</instrument>tenor <instrument>clef</instrument>.
From [ From hence I went to the <placeName>Ospidaletto</placeName>, of which signor <persName>sacchini</persName> is the <persName>master</persName>, and was indeed very much pleased by the composition of part of the famous <music>hymn</music> <music>salve Regina</music>, which was singing when I entered the <placeName>church</placeName>; it was new, spirited, and full of ingenious contrivances for the instruments, which always said something interesting without disturbing the <instrument>voice</instrument>.
Upon the whole, there seemed to be as much genius in this composition as in any I had heard since my arrival in <placeName>Italy</placeName>.
The <persName>performers</persName> here too are all <persName>orphan <persName>girls</persName></persName>; one of them, la <placeName>Ferrarese</placeName>, sung very well, and had a very extraordinary compass of <instrument>voice</instrument>, as she was able to reach the highest E of our <instrument>harpsichords</instrument>, upon which she could dwell a considerable time, in a fair, natural <instrument>voice</instrument>.
Even after this, upon the <placeName>Piazza di s.
Marco</placeName>, I heard a great number of <persName>vagrant <persName>musicians</persName></persName>, some in <instrument>bands</instrument>, accompanying one or two <instrument>voices</instrument>; sometimes a single <instrument>voice</instrument> and <instrument>guitar</instrument>; and sometimes two I or three <instrument>guitars</instrument> together.
Indeed it is not to be wondered at, that the streetmusic here is generally neglected, as <persName>people</persName> are almost stunned with it at <date>every corner</date>; but, however, in justice to the taste and discernment of the <placeName>Italians</placeName>, it must be allowed, that when they do admire, it is something excellent; and then; they never“ damn with faint praise, but express rapture in a manner peculiar to themselves; they seem to agonize with pleasure too great for the aching sense.
They had here, <date>last Carnival</date>, seven <placeName><instrument>opera</instrument>-houses</placeName> open at once, three serious, and four comic, besides four <placeName>play-houses</placeName>, and these were all crowded <date>every night</date>.
<date>Monday 6</date>.
This <date>morning</date> the <persName>Doge</persName> went in procession to the <placeName><placeName>church</placeName> of s.
Giovanni e Paolo</placeName>.
I was not only curious to see this procession, but to hear the music, which I expected would be very considerable, and by a great <persName>band</persName>; however there was only a <music>mass</music> sung in four parts, parts, without other instrument than the <instrument>organ</instrument>, but then it was so good of the kind, so well executed and accompanied, that I do not remember to have received more pleasure from such music.
One of the <persName>organists</persName> of <date>st</date>.
<placeName><persName>Mark</persName>'s <placeName>church</placeName></placeName>, who is in orders, attended, and discovered himself, in his voluntaries and interludes, to be a very masterly <persName>performer</persName>.
The <instrument>voices</instrument> were well chosen, and well assorted, no one stronger than the other; the composition was of <persName>signor <persName>Lotti</persName></persName>, and was truly grave and majestic, consisting of <music>fugues</music> and <music>imitations</music> in the stile of our best old <music><placeName>church</placeName> services</music>, which have been so well selected, and published in so magnificent a manner by <persName>Dr.
Boyce</persName>; all was clear and distinct, no confusion or unnecessary notes; it was even capable of expression, particularly one of the <music>movements</music>, into which the <persName>performers</persName> entered so well, that it affected <persName>me</persName> even to tears.
The <persName>organist</persName> here very judicioussy suffered the <instrument>voices</instrument> to be heard in all their purity, insomuch somuch that I frequently forgot that they were accompanied; upon the whole this seems to be the true stile for the <placeName>church</placeName>: it calls to memory nothing vulgar, light, or prophane; it disposes the mind to philanthrophy, and divests it of its gross and sensual passions.
Indeed my being moved was the mere effect of <instrument>well-</instrument>modulated and <instrument>well-</instrument>measured sounds, for I knew not the words, which were wholly lost by the distance; nor is this species of music at all favourable to poetry: in the answers that are made to the points, the several parts all sing different words, so that no great effects can be produced by them; but notwithstanding this defect, such music as this, in the <date>service</date> of the <placeName>church</placeName>, must ever be allowed to have its merit, however it may be exploded, or unfit for theatrical purposes.
In consequence of a message from <persName>Mr.
Richie</persName>, Chargé des Affaires to his <placeName>Britannic Majesty</placeName>, to whom sir <placeName>James Wright</placeName> had honoured <persName>me</persName> with a <persName>letter</persName>, and who very very politely and kindly was pleased to interest himself effectually in my <date>service</date>, I was this <date>afternoon</date> favoured with a visit from signor <persName>Latilla</persName>, an <persName>eminent <persName>composer</persName></persName> here, and had a long conversation with him relative to the subject of my journey.
I found him to be a plain, sensible <persName>man</persName>, of about sixty years of age, who had both read and thought much concerning the music of the ancients, as well as that of the moderns, to which he has contributed a considerable share for many years past *.
I admired his candour in advising <persName>me</persName> to go to the <placeName>Incurabili</placeName>, to hear the <persName>girls</persName> perform there, with whom he said I should be much pleased.
They are <persName>scholars</persName> of <persName>signor <persName>Galuppi</persName></persName>, who is <persName><instrument>Maestro</instrument> di Capella</persName> of this <placeName>Conservatorio</placeName>.
Unluckily when I arrived there, the performance was begun, however, I had only lost the * Most of the comic <instrument>operas</instrument> performed in <placeName>London</placeName> with such success, in the time of <persName>Pertici</persName> and <persName>Laschi</persName>, were of <persName>Latilla</persName>'s composition; particularly La <persName>Comedia in Comedia</persName>, <music>Don Calascione</music>, and others.
He is uncle to signor Piccini.
L <date>2 overUniversity</date> P ublished online by Ca ( <music>overture</music>, and part of the first <music>air</music>.
The words were taken from three or four of the <music><music>Psalms</music> in Latin</music>, from the <music>hymn</music> <music>salve Regina</music>, and one of the <music>Canticles</music> put into Latin verse, and in dialogue.
I knew not whether I was most delighted with the composition, or with the execution; both were admirable.
signor <persName>Buranello</persName> has preserved all his fire and imagination from the chill blasts of <placeName>Russia</placeName>, This inwhence he is lately returned* genious, entertaining, and elegant <persName>composer</persName> abounds in novelty, in spirit, and in delicacy, and his <persName>scholars</persName> did his music great justice.
several of them had uncommon talents for singing, particularly the <music>Rota</music>, <music>Pasqua Rossi</music>, and the <music>Ortolani</music>; the two last sung the <music>Canticle</music> in dialogue.
The <music>overture</music>, and the whole of this last performance were for two <instrument>orchestras</instrument>.
In the <music>overture</music>, which was full of pretty * <persName>signor <persName>Galuppi</persName></persName> is best known in <placeName>Italy</placeName> by the name of <persName>Buranello</persName>, which he acquired from having been born in the little <placeName>issand of Burano</placeName>, near <placeName>Venice</placeName>.
He is replaced at <placeName>Petersburg</placeName> by signor <placeName>Traetta</placeName>.
pas- 1 passages, the two <instrument>bands</instrument> echoed each other.
There were two <instrument>organs</instrument>, and two pair of <instrument>French <instrument>horns</instrument></instrument>.
In short, I was extremely entertained by this performance, and the whole <persName>company</persName>, which was very nu- merous, seemed equally pleased.
The young <persName>singers</persName>, just mentioned, are absolute nightingales; they have a facility of executing difficult divisions equal to that of <persName>birds</persName>.
They did such things in that way, especially the <music>Rota</music>, as I do not remember to have heard attempted before.
The able <persName>master</persName> was discoverable in all the cadences of these young <persName>subjects</persName>.
The instrumental parts were very well executed, and the whole indicated a superior genius in the <persName>composer</persName> and <persName>conductor</persName> of the performance.
This music, which was of the higher sort of theatric stile, though it was performed in a <placeName>church</placeName>, was not mixed with the <music><placeName>church</placeName> <date>service</date></music>, and the audience sat the whole time as at a <persName>concert</persName>; and, indeed, this might L <date>3</date> might be called a <instrument>concerto</instrument> spirituale with great propriety.
<date>Tuesday 7</date>.
This <date>morning</date> there was a <music>mass</music> in <date>musie</date> at the <placeName><placeName>church</placeName> of s.
Gaetano</placeName>.
It being a great festival, all the treasures and relics were exposed to public view, and there was a very great <persName>crowd</persName>.
The <persName>composer</persName> of the music, and the <persName>person</persName> who beat the time was <persName>signor Menagatto</persName>, a <persName>priest</persName>; I cannot say that I received much pleasure from this performance, the <instrument>organ</instrument> was coarse, and poorly played; the <instrument>voices</instrument> only two indifferent tenors, and a <instrument>base</instrument>, and the composition very common, and unmarked by any stamp of original genius.
The <persName>people</persName> here, at this season, seem to begin to live only at <date>midnight</date>.
Then the <placeName>canals</placeName> are crowded with gondolas, and <date>st</date>.
<placeName><persName>Mark</persName>'s square</placeName> with <persName>company</persName>; the <placeName>banks</placeName> too of the <placeName>canals</placeName> are all peopled, and harmony prevails in every part.
If two of the <persName>common <persName>people</persName></persName> walk together arm in arm, they seem to converse I in song; if there is <persName>company</persName> on the <placeName>water</placeName>, in a <placeName>gondola</placeName>, it is the same; a mere melody, unaccompanied with a second part, is not to be heard in this <placeName>city</placeName>: all the <music>ballads</music> in the streets are sung in duo.
Luckily for <persName>me</persName>, this night, a <placeName>barge</placeName>, in which there was an excellent <persName><persName>band</persName> of music</persName>, consisting of <instrument>violins</instrument>, <instrument>flutes</instrument>, <instrument>horns</instrument>, <instrument>bases</instrument>, and a <instrument>kettle-drum</instrument>, with a pretty good tenor <instrument>voice</instrument>, was on the <placeName>great canal</placeName>, and stopped very near the <placeName>house</placeName> where I lodged; it was a <music><date>piece</date> of gallantry</music>, at the expence of an <persName>inamorato</persName> in order to senerade his <persName>mistress</persName>.
<persName>shakespeare</persName> says of <music>nocturnal music</music>, Methinks it sounds much sweeter than by <date>day</date>.
* silence bestows the virtue on it—I think * The nightingale, if she should sing by <date>day</date>, * When every goose is cackling, would be thought t No better a <persName>musician</persName> than the wren.
Whether the time, place, and manner of performing this music, gave it adventitious and collateral charms, I will not pretend to say; all I know is, that the symphoL4 I symphonies seemed to <persName>me</persName> to be admirable, full of fancy, full of fire; the passages well contrasted; sometimes the graceful, sometimes the pathetic prevailed; and sometimes, however strange it may be thought, even noise and fury had their effect.
No one will I believe, at present, deny the necessity of discord in the composition of music in parts; it seems to be as much the essence of music, as shade is of painting; not only as it improves and <persName>meliorates</persName> concord by opposition and comparison, but, still further, as it becomes a necessary stimulus to the attention, which would languish over a succession of pure concords.
It occasions a momentary distress to the ear, which remains unsatisfied, and even uneasy, till it hears something better; for no musical phrase can end upon a discord, the ear must be satisfied at last.
Now, as discord is allowable, and even necessarily opposed to concord, why may not noise, or a seeming jargon, be opposed to fixed sounds and 3Published online by <placeName>Cambridge Universi 1</placeName> und harmonical proportion?
some of the discords in modern music, unknown till this <placeName>century</placeName>, are what the ear can but just bear, but have a very good effect as to contrast.
The severe laws of preparing and resolving discord, may be too much adhered to for great effects; I am convinced, that provided the ear be at length made amends, there are few dissonances too strong for it.
If, for instance, the five sounds c.
d.
e.
f.
g, are all struck at the same instant on the <instrument>harpsichord</instrument>, provided the d and the f are taken soon off, and the three others remain, the ear will not suffer much by the first shock.
Or, still further; if, instead of the five sounds above-mentioned, the following are struck; c.
dx.
e.
fx.
g and the d and ff are not held on so long as thè rest, all will end to the satisfaction of the offended ear.
<date><date>Wednesday</date> 8</date>.
This <date>day</date> was remark- able for no enquiry relative to the present state of music in <placeName>Italy</placeName>; however it deserves <persName>1541</persName> deserves mention here, on account of the opportunity it afforded <persName>me</persName> of conversing with the <persName><persName>Abate</persName> Martini</persName>, one of the best <persName>judges</persName> of every part of music, ancient and modern, that I had yet met with.
He is an able <persName>mathematician</persName>, a <persName>composer</persName>, and <persName>performer</persName>.
He had travelled into <placeName>Grecce</placeName>, in order to make observations in geography, agriculture, and natural history, but being unable to satisfy himself as he expected, his pride was so hurt by the disappointment, that he would not publish any of his remarks or discoveries.
Among other curious enquires, he made many concerning the music of the modern <persName>Greeks</persName>, in hopes it would throw some light upon that of the ancient.
He knows, I believe, as much as any one else, about the systems of <persName>Pythagoras</persName>, <persName>Ptolemy</persName>, and the <persName>writers</persName> collected by <persName>Meibomius</persName>, as well as of <persName>Rameau</persName> and <persName>Tartini</persName>.
He is a great <persName>admirer</persName> of the <music>works of Marcello</music>, and sings by heart all his <music>cantatas</music> and best melodies.
After reading I 1 reading my plan, which we discussed article by article, he entered much into my views; shewed <persName>me</persName> his <persName>Grecian</persName> and other manuscript papers, and I had great reason to be satisfied both with my reception, and the information with which he favoured <persName>me</persName>.
<date>9th</date>.
I had this <date>afternoon</date> another long conversation with the same learned <persName>gentleman</persName>, who was so obliging as to bring his manuscript papers concerning Greek music, and to desire my acceptance of them.
I could not help regarding this present as a valuable acquisition, for though the materials it contained were too few for his original purpose of forming a booi, they appeared likely to be of importance in the course of a work, in which it is proposed to treat not only of <music>ancient music</music>, but of the <music>national music</music> of most parts of the <placeName>world</placeName>, from whence specimens, or accounts well authenticated can be had.
The <persName>Abate</persName> has, however, collected a set of apophthegms or pro156 proverbs, which he intends to publish, and which will discover the manners and misery of the modern <persName>Greeks</persName>, perhaps more effectually than any other work could do.
There was music this <date>evening</date> at the <placeName><placeName>church</placeName> of <date>st</date></placeName>.
Laurence, composed and directed by signor <persName>sacchini</persName>, at which, as it was the vigil of this saint, there was a great <persName>crowd</persName>.
I suffered, as well as every one else, too much by the heat, perhaps, to be easily pleased, and the composition seemed rather more common than that I had heard of this ingenious <persName>master</persName> before; however, the vocal parts were not so well performed, as there were no other <persName>singers</persName> than those of <date>st</date>.
<placeName><persName>Mark</persName>'s <placeName>church</placeName></placeName>, who most excel in mere <music><placeName>church</placeName> music</music>, accompanied only by the <instrument>organ</instrument>.
The <instrument>voices</instrument> were not good enough sor long <music>solo parts</music>, nor strong enough to get through a large <persName>band</persName>; however there were many very pleasing and agreeable <music>movements</music>, and some of the <music>chorusses</music> were were well worked in the <music>fugue</music> and <persName>oratorio</persName> way.
But for this kind of music, that of <instrument>Handel</instrument> will, I believe, ever stand superior to all other <persName>writers</persName>; at least I have heard nothing yet on the <placeName>continent</placeName> of equal force and effect.
There is often in the compositions of others, more melody in the <music>solo parts</music>, more delicacy, and more light and shade, but as to harmony and contrivance, no one comes near him by many degrees.
I must confess that I had heard some of <persName><instrument>Handel</instrument>'s music</persName> so long, and often so ill performed, that I was somewhat tired and disgusted with it; but my <placeName>Italian</placeName> journey, instead of lowering the esteem I ever had for the best writings of that truly great <persName>artist</persName>, exalted them in my opinion, and at my return renewed my pleasure in hearing them performed.
As yet I had heard little but <music><placeName>church</placeName> music</music> in <placeName>Italy</placeName>; however, in that stile, with instruments, all other compositions appeared feeble by comparison.
The <persName>subjects</persName> of the <music>fugues</music> were, in general, 1 ral, trivial and common, and the manner of working them dry and artless.
Indeed the <placeName>church</placeName> stile, without instruments, except the <instrument>organ</instrument>, was well known in <placeName>Italy</placeName>, and all over <placeName>Europe</placeName>, long before <instrument>Handel</instrument>'s time; and melody is certainly much refined since.
it is more graceful, more pathetic, and even more gay; but for <instrument>counter-</instrument>point, <music>fugues</music>, and <music>chorusses</music> of many <instrument>voices</instrument>, with instruments, I repeat it, I neither have heard, nor do I ever expect to hear him equalled.
<date>10th</date>.
This <date>morning</date> I went again to the <placeName>church</placeName> of the <placeName>convent of <date>st</date></placeName>.
Laurence, where, besides a <music>mass</music> of signor <persName>sacchini</persName>'s composition, I heard <persName>signor Nazzari</persName>, the first <instrument>violin</instrument> of <placeName>Venice</placeName>, play a <instrument>concerto</instrument>; but we have long heard that instrument so well performed upon in <placeName>England</placeName>, that nothing is left to admire.
However, <persName>signor Nazzari</persName> is certainly a very neat and pleasing <persName>player</persName>; his tone is even, sweet, and full; he plays with great facility and expression, and is, upon the whole, I whole, the best <persName>solo <persName>player</persName></persName> I had heard on this side the Alps.
Argus is said to have had an hundred eyes, and Fame has been painted by the <persName>poets</persName> all tongues; in this place one wishes to be all ears for music, and all eyes for painting and architecture.
<date>To-<date>day</date></date> there were so many temptations to a <persName>lover</persName> of harmony, that it was difficult for him to chuse; for, besides the <placeName>four <placeName>conservatorios</placeName></placeName>, there were several <placeName>accademias</placeName> or <placeName>private</placeName> concerts.
I was invited to one, which assembles on all <date>festivals</date>, in order to sing the <music>works of Marcello</music>, without other accompaniment than a <instrument>harpsichord</instrument>; and as this was different from any other I had been at in <placeName>Italy</placeName>, I accepted the invitation, though I wished very much to be at the <placeName>Incurabili</placeName>, where I was sure of entertainment from <persName>Buranello</persName> and his <persName>scholars</persName>.
several of Marcello's <music>Psalms</music> were here very well sung by the <persName><persName>Abate</persName> Martini</persName> and some other dilettanti, among whom one had had a very good <instrument>base</instrument> <instrument>voice</instrument>, and, between the <music>Psalms</music>, sung Marcello s famous <music>cantata</music> called <persName>Cassandra</persName>, where this <persName>composer</persName> has entirely sacrificed the music to the poetry, by changing the time or stile of his movement at every new idea which occurs in the words; this may, perhaps, shew a <persName>composer</persName> to be a very sensible <persName>man</persName>, but at the same time it must discover him to be of a very phlegmatic turn, and wholly free from the enthusiasm of a creative musical genius.
And, indeed, since melody has been allied to grace and fancy, musical disjointed thoughts on various <persName>subjects</persName>, would be but ill received by the public.
One of these <persName><persName>gentlemen</persName> <persName>performers</persName></persName> was old enough to remember very well the celebrated <music>Benedetto Marcello</music>, who has been dead <date>forty-four</date> years, and gave <persName>me</persName> several anecdotes about him; his family, which is <persName>noble</persName>, still subsists, and the head of it is now <persName>ambassador</persName> from the <placeName>Venetian</placeName> state at the <placeName>Porte</placeName>.
<date>11th</date>.
<date>11th</date>.
This <date>afternoon</date> I went again to the <placeName>Pietà</placeName>; there was not much <persName>company</persName>, and the <persName>girls</persName> played a thousand tricks in singing, particularly in the <music>duets</music>, where there was a trial of skill and of natural powers, as who could go highest, lowest, swell a note the longest, or run divisions with the greatest rapidity.
They always finish with a <music>symphony</music>; and last <date>Wednesday</date> they played one by sarte, which I had before heard in <placeName>England</placeName>, at the <placeName><instrument>opera</instrument> of the Olimpiade</placeName>.
The <persName>band</persName> here is certainly very powerful, as there are in the <placeName>hospital</placeName> above a thousand <persName>girls</persName>, and out of these there are seventy <persName>musicians</persName>, vocal and instrumental; at each of the other three <placeName>hospitals</placeName> there are not above forty, as I was informed by signor <persName>L’Atilla</persName>, which are chosen out of about a hundred <persName>orphans</persName>, as the orignal establishment requires.
But it has been known that a <persName>child</persName>, with a fine <instrument>voice</instrument>, has been taken into these <placeName>hospitals</placeName> before it was bereaved of father or <persName>mother</persName>.
<music>Children</music> are someI sometimes brought hither to be educated from the <placeName>towns</placeName> belonging to the <placeName>Venetian</placeName> state, upon the <placeName>Continent</placeName>; from <placeName>Padua</placeName>, <placeName>Verona</placeName>, Brescia, and even from other places, still more distant; for <persName>Francesca Gabrieli</persName> came from <placeName>Ferrara</placeName>, and is therefore called the <placeName>Ferrarese</placeName>.
The <placeName>Conservatorio</placeName> of the <placeName>Pietà</placeName> has heretofore been the most celebrated for its <persName>band</persName>, and the <placeName>Mendicanti</placeName> for <instrument>voices</instrument>; but in the <instrument>voices</instrument> time and accident may occasion great alterations; the <persName>master</persName> may give a <persName>celebrity</persName> to a <placeName>school</placeName> of this kind, both by his compositions and abilities in teaching; and as to <instrument>voices</instrument>, nature may sometimes be more kind to the <persName>subjects</persName> of one <placeName>hospital</placeName> than another; but as the number is greater at the <placeName>Pietà</placeName> than at the rest, and consequently the chances of superior qualifications more, it is natural to suppose that this <placeName>hospital</placeName> will in general have the best <persName>band</persName> and the best <instrument>voices</instrument>.
At present, the great abilities of <persName>signor <persName>Galuppi</persName></persName> are conspicuous in the performances I unces at the <placeName>Incurabili</placeName>, which is, in point of music, singing, and <instrument>orchestra</instrument>, in my opinion, superior to the rest.
Next to that, the <placeName>Ospidaletto</placeName> takes place of the other two; so that the <placeName>Pietà</placeName> seems to enjoy the reputation of being the <placeName>best <placeName>school</placeName></placeName>, not for what it does now, but for what it has done, heretofore.
<date>sunday 12</date>.
This <date>morning</date>, after hearing high <music>mass</music> well performed at <date>st</date>.
<persName>Mark</persName> s, I went to the <placeName>patriarchal <placeName><placeName>church</placeName> of <date>st</date></placeName></placeName>.
<persName>Peter</persName>, and heard it again there, accompanied by a very fine <instrument>organ</instrument>, well played on by one of the <persName>priests</persName>; after that I went to the <placeName><placeName>Franciscans</placeName> <placeName>church</placeName></placeName>, where one of the <persName>Friars</persName> likewise was <persName>organist</persName>, but he played in a very superior manner, both as to taste and harmony.
though I visited these <placeName>churches</placeName> for the sake of music, it was impossible to keep my eyes off the pictures and architecture.
But it was here I began to find that these two objects of sight were not so remote from my chief purpose of writing a history M 2 tory of the pleasures of the ear, as I at first imagined; for I frequently, in the old <persName>masters</persName>, met with representations of musical instruments, either of their own times, or at least such as they imagined to be in use at the time when the action of the <date>piece</date> happened; thus I observed in a famous picture of the <placeName>Marriage of Cana by <persName>P.
Veronese</persName></placeName>, in the <placeName>sacristy of s.
Georgio Maggiore</placeName>, a <persName>concert</persName>, with a variety of instruments, of all which I have made a memorandum: and I saw this <date>morning</date>, at the <placeName>Franciscans</placeName>, a little picture under the <placeName>pulpit</placeName>, by san Croce, which is much admired, and thought to be a good deal in the stile of <persName>Raphael</persName>, in which is a <placeName><persName>concert</persName> of cherubs</placeName> and <music>seraphs</music>; and I observed among several different kinds of <instrument>lutes</instrument> and <instrument>guitars</instrument>, an instrument played with a <instrument>bow</instrument>, resting, like a <instrument>violin</instrument>, upon the shoulder of the <persName>performer</persName>, but it had six strings.
After I had seen these, and some more <placeName>churches</placeName>, I had the honour of a long <persName>con1651</persName> conversation with <persName>il Conte Torre Taxis</persName>, who is here a <persName>person</persName> of great weight * he is <persName>superintendant-</persName>general of the <placeName>German</placeName> and <placeName><placeName>Venetian</placeName> post-office</placeName>, was a great <persName>friend</persName> of <persName>Tartini</persName>, is now in possession of all his Ms.
compositions, shewed <persName>me</persName> a great number of them, and has defended his <persName>friend</persName> in a <music>pamphlet</music>, of which he did <persName>me</persName> the honour to give <persName>me</persName> a copy, against some remarks made upon his <persName>Trattato di Musica</persName>, by <persName>M.
Rousseau</persName>, in his Dict.
de Musique.
This <persName>nobleman</persName>, though young, seems to possess great musical erudition; to have profited from the converse and correspondence of <persName>Tartini</persName>, and to be an <persName>enthusiast</persName> for the arts in general.
I had great pleasure in his conversation, in which I communicated to him my plan of a <placeName>History of Music</placeName>, and was pleased and enlightened by his observations.
* He is of the same family with that <instrument><placeName>German</placeName> prince</instrument>, better known in <placeName>France</placeName> and <placeName>England</placeName> by the name of <persName>Tour Taxis</persName>.
In M <date>3</date> In the <date>afternoon</date> I stopped a little while at the new <placeName>church</placeName> of the <placeName>Jesuati</placeName>, where I heard the <instrument>organ</instrument> played with a very uncommon brilliancy of execution, by one of the <persName>Dominicans</persName>.
It was indeed a stile of playing more suitable to the <instrument>harpsichord</instrument> than <instrument>organ</instrument>, but, in its way, was very masterly and powerful.
There are some reed stops in this instrument which I had never heard before, and with which the <persName>performer</persName> produced effects that I was unable to account for.
I had not time to make enquiries, as I took this <placeName>church</placeName> only in my way to the <placeName>Incurabili</placeName>, where I was so pleased, both with the composition and performance, that in speaking of them I shall find it difficult to avoid <music>hyperboles</music>.
It seems as if the genius of <persName>signor <persName>Galuppi</persName></persName>, like that of <persName>Titian</persName>, became more animated by age.
He cannot now be less than seventy years old, and yet it is generally allowed here that his last <instrument>operas</instrument>, and his last compositions for the <placeName>church</placeName>, abound abound with more spirit, taste, and fancy, than those of any other period of his life.
This <date>evening</date> the Latin <music>Psalms</music> that were sung by the <persName>orphan <persName>girls</persName></persName>, gave <persName>me</persName> great reason to concur in the common opinion, for out of ten or twelve <music>movements</music>, there was not one that could be pronounced indifferent.
There were several admirable, accompanied <persName>recitatives</persName>, and the whole abounded with new passages, with good taste, good harmony, and good sense.
His accompaniments, in particular, are always ingenious, but, though full, free from that kind of confusion which disturbs and covers the <instrument>voice</instrument>.
I must likewise do justice to the <instrument>orchestra</instrument>, which is here under the most exact discipline; no one of the instrumental <persName>performers</persName> seemed ambitious of shining at the expence of the vocal part, but all were under that kind of subordination which is requisite in a <persName>servant</persName> to a superior.
Of these young <persName>singers</persName> I have spoken rather warmly before, but in this performance they disM4 discovered still new talents and new cultivation.
Their music of <date>to-night</date> was rather more grave than that which I had heard here before, and I thought they were more firm in it; that their intonations were more exact, and, as more time was allowed for it, a greater volume of <instrument>voice</instrument> by the two principal <persName>subjects</persName> was thrown out.
But in their closes, I know not which astonished <persName>me</persName> most, the compass of <instrument>voice</instrument>, variety of passages, or rapidity of execution; indeed all were such as would have merited and received great applause in the first <instrument>operas</instrument> of <placeName>Europe</placeName>.
I dwell the longer on these performances, as, at present, the theatres of <placeName>Venice</placeName> are all shut; but the only difference between this kind of <music><placeName>church</placeName> music</music>, and that of the drama, consists in the <music>chorusses</music>; those of the <placeName>church</placeName> are long, elaborate, and sometimes well written.
Those who suppose all the <music><placeName>church</placeName> music</music> of <placeName>Italy</placeName> to be as light and <music>airy</music> as that of the <instrument>opera</instrument>, are mistaken; it is only on <date>festivals</date> that modern modern music can be heard in any of the <placeName>churches</placeName>.
The music of the <placeName>cathedrals</placeName>, on common days, is in a stile as grave and as ancient as that of our <music><placeName>church</placeName> services</music> of two hundred years standing; and in the <placeName>parish <placeName>churches</placeName></placeName> it is a mere canto fermo, or chant, sung in unison by the <persName>priests</persName> only; sometimes with the <instrument>organ</instrument>, but more frequently without.
If we compare the music os Mr.
<persName><instrument>Handel</instrument>'s first</persName> <persName>oratorios</persName> with the <instrument>operas</instrument> he composed about the same time, it will appear that the <music>airs</music> of the one are often as gay as those of the other.
And as to the <music>chorusses</music> of an <instrument>opera</instrument>, which are all to be in action, and performed by memory, they must of course be shorter and less laboured than those of an <persName>oratorio</persName>, where every <persName>singer</persName> has his part before him, and where a <persName>composer</persName> is allowed sufficient time to display his abilities in every species of what is called by <persName>musicians</persName> good writing.
From 1 From the <placeName>Incurabili</placeName> I had the honour to be carried by his Excellency signor <persName>Murin Giorgi</persName>, to an accademia, at the <persName>Casa Grimani</persName>, where I first had the pleasure to hear signora <persName>Baffa</persName>, a <persName><persName>noble</persName> <placeName>Venetian</placeName></persName> <persName>lady</persName>.
she has long been reckoned the best <persName>performer</persName> on the <instrument>harpsichord</instrument> of all the <persName>ladies</persName> of <placeName>Venice</placeName>; and I found that she played very neatly, and with much taste and judgment.
The <persName>company</persName> consisted of the chief nobility of <placeName>Venice</placeName>, the three <persName>persons</persName> Ihave named being among the first class.
They did great justice in this assembly to the abilities of <persName>Mrs.
<persName>Cassandra</persName> Wynn</persName>, from <placeName>England</placeName>, who was there last <date>year</date>, and had left behind her the character of a very great <persName>player</persName>.
<date>Tuesday 14</date>.
This <date>evening</date> being the vigil of the Assumption, there were musical performances at three different <placeName>churches</placeName>.
I went first to that of the <placeName>Celestia</placeName>; the <instrument>vespers</instrument> were composed and directed by the <persName><instrument>Maestro</instrument> of the</persName> <placeName>Pietà</placeName>, signor I signor <persName>Furlanetto</persName>; there were two <instrument>orchestras</instrument>, both well filled with vocal and instrumental <persName>performers</persName>.
the <music>overture</music> was spirited, and the first <music>chorus</music> good, in <persName>Contra Punto</persName>; then there was a long <music>symphony</music> in dialogue, between the two <instrument>orchestras</instrument>, and an <music>air</music> well accompanied, though but indifferently sung.
After this an <music>air</music> in dialogue with the <music>chorus</music>, which had a good effect: an <music>air</music> for a tenor <instrument>voice</instrument>, of little merit, and one for a <instrument>base</instrument>, which was ingenioussy put together, making use by turns of all the principal instruments: I did not stay out the whole performance, but what <placeName>Iheard</placeName> seemed superior to any composition that I had before met with of this <persName>author</persName>; he availed himself of the two <instrument>orchestras</instrument>, and produced several effects which, with one, would have been impracticable.
From hence I went to the <placeName>Ospidaletto</placeName>, where the music and <persName>musicians</persName> spoke a different language.
The performance was a Latin <persName>oratorio</persName>; <music>Machabaeorum Mater</music>; the the music was by signor <persName>sacchini</persName>; there were six characters in it, the principal was persormed by <persName>Francesca Gabrieli</persName>: it was divided into two parts; the first was over before I arrived, for which I was very sorry, as what remained delighted <persName>me</persName> extremely, both as to the composition, which was excellent, and the singing which had infinite merit.
When I entered the <placeName><placeName>church</placeName> the <placeName>Ferrarese</placeName></placeName> was speaking an admirable accompanied <music>recitative</music> in such a manner as is seldom heard; it was terminated by a <music>Bravura <music>air</music></music>, with a pathetic second part in <placeName>Jomelli's <persName>oratorio</persName> style</placeName>, but by no means in his passages; there was then a <music>recitative</music> and slow <music>air</music> by <persName>Laura Conti</persName>, who is possessed of no great power of <instrument>voice</instrument>; it is a mere voce di Camera; but she has infinite expression and taste, and charmed <persName>me</persName> in a different way.
then followed another <music>recitative</music>, and after it a <persName>duet</persName>, which was truly sublime; it was extremely well executed by <persName>Domenica Pasquati</persName> and <persName>Ippolita</persName> I <persName>1731 <persName>Ippolita</persName> santi</persName>; upon the whole, signor <persName>sacchini</persName> rises in my opinion, and according to my feelings and intelligence he is the second in <placeName>Venice</placeName>, having no superior there but <persName>signor <persName>Galuppi</persName></persName>.
The singing I heard at this <placeName><placeName>hospital</placeName> <date>to-night</date></placeName> would, as well as that of the <placeName>Mendicanti</placeName>, I am certain, receive great applause in the first <placeName><instrument>opera</instrument> of <placeName>Europe</placeName></placeName>.
<date><date>Wednesday</date> 15</date>.
I went this <date>morning</date> to <date>st</date>.
<placeName><persName>Mark</persName>’s <placeName>church</placeName></placeName>, at which, being a festival, the <persName>doge</persName> was present.
I there heard high <music>mass</music> performed under the direction of <persName>signor <persName>Galuppi</persName></persName>, <persName>composer</persName> of the music.
Upon this occasion there were six <instrument>orchestras</instrument>, two great <persName>ones</persName> in the <placeName>galleries</placeName> of the two principal <instrument>organs</instrument>, and four less, two on a side, in which there were likewise small <instrument>organs</instrument>.
I was placed very advantageoussy in one of the great <instrument>organ</instrument> lofts, with signor L'Atilla, The <persName>muassistant</persName> to <persName>signor <persName>Galuppi</persName></persName>* * This instrument has <instrument>pedals</instrument>, and but one row of <instrument>box</instrument> keys.
sic, I sic, which was in general full and grave, had a great effect, though this <placeName>church</placeName> is not very happily formed for music, as it has five <placeName>domes</placeName> or cupolas, by which the sound is too much broken and reverberated before it reaches the ear.
From hence I went again to the <placeName>Celestià</placeName>, which <placeName>church</placeName> was very much crowded.
The <music>mass</music> was set to music by signor <persName>Furlanetto</persName>, <persName>master</persName> to the <placeName>Pictà</placeName>: the resources of this <persName>composer</persName> are very few; he has little fire and less variety, but he sins more on the side of genius than learning, as his harmony is good, and modulation regular and warrantable; but I must own, that his music is to <persName>me</persName> tiresome, and leaves behind it a languor and dissatisfaction; wher as that of <persName>signor <persName>Galuppi</persName></persName> and <persName>sacchini</persName> always exhilerates and <persName>enlivens</persName>.
signor Nazari played here a <instrument>concerto</instrument> on the <instrument>violin</instrument> in a very neat and pleasing manner.
I know not of whose composition, but it was by no means remarkable for novelty.
After <date>dinner</date> I went I 1 went to the <placeName><placeName>church</placeName> of santa Maria Mag</placeName>.
giore to see some pictures, and stumbled on music, but such music as I did not think it possible for the <persName>people</persName> of <placeName>Italy</placeName> to bear.
The <instrument>organ</instrument> was out of tune, other instruments out of time, and the <instrument>voices</instrument> were both; then the composition seemed just such stuff as a <persName>boy</persName> who was learning <instrument>counter-</instrument>point would produce after the first two or three lessons.
After I had seen the two best pictures in the <placeName>church</placeName>, the <placeName>famous <date>st</date></placeName>.
<persName>John</persName> the <placeName>Baptist</placeName>, by <persName>Titian</persName>, and <placeName>Noah's ark by Giacomo Bassano</placeName>, I ran away from this music to the <placeName>Incurabili</placeName>, where <persName>Buranello</persName>'s nightingales, the <music>Rota</music>, and <music>Pasqua Rossi</music>, poured balm into my wounded ears.
There was not much <persName>company</persName>, and the <persName>girls</persName> did not exert themselves; however, after what I had just heard, their performance was ravishing; and it was not without regret that I reflected upon this being the last time I should hear it.
<date>Thursday 1761 Thursday 16</date>.
My visit to <persName>signor <persName>Galuppi</persName></persName> this <date>morning</date> was long, profitable, and entertaining.
I was very glad to find upon seeing him, that time had spared the <persName>person</persName> as well as genius of this excellent <persName>composer</persName>.
He is still lively and alert, and likely to delight the <placeName>lovers of music</placeName> many years.
His character and conversation are natural, intelligent, and agreeable.
He is in figure little and thin, but has very much the look of a <persName>gentleman</persName>.
<persName>signor <persName>Galuppi</persName></persName> was a <persName>scholar</persName> of the famous <persName>Lotti</persName>, and very early taken notice of as a good <persName>harpfichord <persName>player</persName></persName>, and a genius in composition.
He was so obliging as to present <persName>me</persName> to signora <persName>Galuppi</persName>; to shew <persName>me</persName> his <placeName>house</placeName>; an admirable picture of a sleeping <persName>child</persName>, by <persName>P.
Veronese</persName>, which has been long in his wife's family; and to carry <persName>me</persName> into his <persName>working-room</persName>, with only a little <instrument>clavichord</instrument> in it, where, he told <persName>me</persName>, he dirtied paper.
His family has been very large, but all his <persName>children</persName>, except three I three or four, are now well married.
He has the appearance of a regular family <persName>man</persName>, and is esteemed at <placeName>Venice</placeName> as much for his <placeName>private</placeName> character as for his public talents.
He seems, however, rather hurt at the encouragement and protection which some ecclesiastical dunces, among whom is F—, meet with as <persName>composers</persName> here.
Indeed, except <persName>sacchini</persName>, his second, he stands so high among the present race of <persName>musicians</persName> in <placeName>Venice</placeName>, that he seems a <persName>giant</persName> among dwarfs: he was so obliging, at my request, as to promise <persName>me</persName> a <music><date>piece</date> of his composition</music>, which has not yet been made public, as a <persName>relick</persName> and mark of his friendship.
I shewed him my plan, and we talked over that, and music and <persName>musicians</persName>, very cordially, and with similar sentiments: his definition of good music I think admirable, and though short, very comprehensive.
It consists, he fays, ot vaghezza, chiarezza, e buona modulazione*.
He and signor <persName>LA</persName>* Beauty, clearness, and <music>geod</music> modulation.
tilla, tilla, among many other particulars, recollected the names of all the great <persName>masters</persName> of the <placeName>conservatorios</placeName>, and had patience to let <persName>me</persName> write them down.
These <persName>gentlemen</persName> likewise informed <persName>me</persName> that the expence of the <placeName>conservatorios</placeName>, on account of music, is very inconsiderable, there being but sive or six <persName>masters</persName> to each for singing and the several instruments, as the <persName>elder <persName>girls</persName></persName> teach the younger.
The <persName>Macstro di Capella</persName> seldom does more than compose and direct: sometimes, indeed, he writes down closes, and usually attends the <date>last rehearsal</date> and first public performance.
A succession of able <persName>masters</persName> has constantly been employed in these <placeName>schools</placeName>: <persName>Hasse</persName> was once <instrument>Maestro</instrument> to the <placeName>Incurabili</placeName>, and has left a <music>Miserere</music>, which is still performed there in Passion Week, and <persName>18</persName>, according to the <persName><persName>Abate</persName> Martini</persName>, a wonderful composition * I obtained, before I left <placeName>Venice</placeName>, a copy of it; and since my arrival in <placeName>England</placeName>, I have been honoured I <persName>signor <persName>Galuppi</persName></persName> seemed to have full employment here, even in summer, when there are no <instrument>operas</instrument>, as he is first <persName><instrument>Maestro</instrument> di Capella</persName> of <date>st</date>.
<persName>Mark</persName>, and of the <placeName>Incurabili</placeName>.
He has a hundred <persName>zechins</persName> a <date>year</date> as domestic <persName>organist</persName> to the family of <persName>Gritti</persName>, and is <persName>organist</persName> of another <placeName>church</placeName>, of which Ihave forgot the name.
He certainly merits all that can be done for him, being one of the few remaining original <music>geniusses</music> of the <placeName>best <placeName>school</placeName></placeName> perhaps that <placeName>Italy</placeName> ever saw.
His compositions are always ingenious and natural, and I may add, that he is a good contrapuntist, and a <persName>friend</persName> to poetry.
The first appears by his scores, and the latter by the melodies he sets to words, in which the expression of his music always corresponds with the sense of the <persName>author</persName>, and often improves it.
His compositions for the <placeName>church</placeName> are but little honoured with a <persName>letter</persName> from <persName>Count Bujovich</persName>, of <placeName>Venice</placeName>, with several interesting particulars relative to the rise and progress of these musical institutions.
N 2 known known in <placeName>England</placeName>; to <persName>me</persName> they appear excellent*; for though many of the <music>airs</music> are in the <placeName><instrument>opera</instrument> stile</placeName>, yet, upon occasion, he shews himself to be a very able <persName>writer</persName> in the true <placeName>church</placeName> stile, which is grave, with good harmony, good modulation, and <music>fugues</music> well worked.
I was this <date>evening</date> at a second Accademia, at <persName>signor Grimani</persName>'s, which was much more considerable than the first.
signor <persName>sacchini</persName> was there, and several of the principal <persName>musicians</persName> of <placeName>Venice</placeName>.
La <persName>signora Regina Zocchi</persName>, a <persName>lady</persName> who had her musical education at the <placeName>Incurabili</placeName>, under the celebrated signor <persName>Hasse</persName>, and who is now well married, and received, and even courted by the first <persName>people</persName> here, sung: she has a very powerful <instrument>voice</instrument>, and good shake, with great volubility and expression.
<persName>D.
Flaminio Tomj</persName>, who has a mere <persName>Voce di Camera</persName>, sung *I procured at <placeName>Venice</placeName>, some of his <music>motets</music>; and <placeName>Giaseppe</placeName>, an excellent copiest there, undertook to transcribe, and send after <persName>me</persName>, two or three of his <persName>masses</persName>.
with I 1 with exquisite taste.
La signora <persName>Baffa</persName> performed on the <instrument>harpsichord</instrument>, two or three <instrument>concertos</instrument> with much grace and precision.
Add to this, that the whole was well heard by a very large <persName>company</persName>, composed of the first nobility of <placeName>Venice</placeName>, among whom was signor <persName>Mocenigo</persName>, son to the present <persName>doge</persName>.
<date>Friday 17</date>.
I had this <date>morning</date> the honour of a second <persName>interview</persName> with <persName>Count Torre Taxis</persName>, during which, I had the pleasure to hear his excellency perform on the <instrument>harpsichord</instrument>, of which instrument he is an able <persName>master</persName>; he played voluntaries for a considerable time, in which he discovered much skill in modulation, and I found him worthy of a place on the upper form of the <music><persName>Tartini</persName> <placeName>school</placeName></music>.
He shewed <persName>me</persName> a great number of <persName>masses</persName>, <music>motets</music>, and <placeName><persName>oratorios</persName> of his composition</placeName>, for though young, he is already a very voluminous <persName>writer</persName>.
He is possessed of a very curious keyed instrument which was made at <placeName>Berlin</placeName>, under the the direction of his Prussian Majesty: it is, in shape, like a large <instrument>clavichord</instrument>, has several changes ofstops, and is occasionally a <instrument>harp</instrument>, a <instrument>harpsichord</instrument>, a <instrument>lute</instrument>, or <instrument>piano</instrument> forte; but the most curious property of this instrument is, that by drawing out the keys the <instrument>hammers</instrument> are transferred to different strings, by which means a composition may be transposed half a note, a whole note, or a <instrument>flat</instrument> third lower at pleasure, without the embarrassment of different notes or <music>clefs</music>, real or imaginary.
Among the Dilettanti here, besides <persName>Count Taxis</persName>, there is a <persName><persName>noble</persName> <placeName>Venetian</placeName></persName>, signor <persName>Giovan Cornaro</persName>, remarkable for his genius and skill in composition: he had composed a <music>mass</music> for a great festival at a <placeName><placeName>church</placeName> in <placeName>Padua</placeName></placeName>, which was performed there, while I was at <placeName>Venice</placeName>, with an immense <persName><persName>band</persName> of <instrument>voices</instrument></persName> and instruments.
This <date>evening</date>, in order to make myself more fully acquainted with the nature 1831 ture of the <placeName>conservatorios</placeName>, and to finissi my musical enquiries here, I obtained permission to be admitted into the <placeName>music <placeName>school</placeName> of the <placeName>Mendicanti</placeName></placeName>, and was favoured with a <persName>concert</persName>, which was performed wholly on my account, and lasted two hours, by the best vocal and instrumental <persName>performers</persName> of this <placeName>hospital</placeName>: it was really curious to see, as well as to hearevery part of this excellent <persName>concert</persName>, performed by <persName>females</persName>, <instrument>violins</instrument>, tenors, <instrument>bases</instrument>, <instrument>harpsichord</instrument>, <instrument>French <instrument>horns</instrument></instrument>, and even double <instrument>bases</instrument>; and there was a <persName>prioress</persName>, a <persName>person</persName> in years, who presided: the first <instrument>violin</instrument> was very well played by <persName>Antonia Cubli</persName>, of Greek extraction; the <instrument>harpsichord</instrument> sometimes by <persName>Francesca Rossi</persName>, <persName>maestra</persName> del coro, and sometimes by others; these young <persName>persons</persName> frequently change instruments.
The singing was really excellent in different <music>stiles</music>; <persName>Laura Risegari</persName> and <music>Giacoma Frari</music>, had very powerful <instrument>voices</instrument>, capable of filling a <instrument>large theatre</instrument>; these sung bravura <persName>songs</persName>, and <placeName>capital</placeName> N4 scenes scenes selected from <placeName>Italian</placeName> <instrument>operas</instrument>; and <persName>Francesca Tomj</persName>, sister to the <persName>Abate</persName> of that name, and <persName>Antonia Lucuvich</persName>, whose <instrument>voices</instrument> were more delicate, confined themselves chiefly to pathetic <persName>songs</persName>, of taste and expression.
The whole was very judiciously mixed; no two <music>airs</music> of a sort followed each other, and there seemed to be great decorum and good discipline observed in every particular; for these admirable <persName>performers</persName>, who are of different ages, all behaved with great propriety, and seemed to be well educated.
It was here that the two celebrated <persName>female <persName>performers</persName></persName>, the <persName>Archiapate</persName>, now signora <persName>Guglielmi</persName>, and signora <persName>Maddalena Lombardini</persName> sirmen, who have received such great and just applause in <placeName>England</placeName>, had their musical instructions.
If I could have staid a few days longer at <placeName>Venice</placeName>, I might have enjoyed the same kind of entertainment at the other three <placeName>conservatorios</placeName>, having been tempted to continue there by such an offer from a <persName>friend</persName> J <persName>friend</persName> who had interest sufficient to procure <persName>me</persName> a sight of the interior discipline of these admirable <placeName>musical seminaries</placeName>; and I declined this obliging offer with the greater reluctance, as there is not in all <placeName>Italy</placeName>, any establishment of the same kind; but being willing to divide the time I had allowed myself for the enquiries I had to make there as equally as possible, I resisted that temptation as well as several other offers with which I was honoured, from some of the principal nobility, of being admitted to their <placeName>private</placeName> concerts; and thus far for the <placeName>honour of <placeName>Italy</placeName></placeName>, as well as for my own, I must say, that I met with the politest treatment, and greatest encouragement and assistance imaginable, wherever I stopt.
At <placeName>Venice</placeName> my expectations were greatly surpassed, as 1 had always been told that the inhabitants, particularly the better sort, were reserved and difficult of access.
I was indebted for much of my entertainment and information at <placeName>Venice</placeName>, to the assiduity and friendihip of <persName>Mr.
Edwards</persName>, a young <persName>gentleman</persName> who was born in <placeName>England</placeName>, but has lived so long in this <placeName>city</placeName>, that he has wholly lost his vernanacular tongue.
With this <persName>gentleman</persName>, and <persName>D.
Flaminio Tomj</persName>, I went from the <placeName>Conservatorio</placeName> of the <placeName>Mendicanti</placeName>, to <persName>signor Grimani</persName>'s.
here the <persName><persName>Abate</persName> Tomj</persName> sung two or three pathetic <music>airs</music> with more taste than I can remember to have heard since the death of <persName>Palma</persName>.
There was a great deal of <persName>company</persName>, and the musical performances of various kinds continued till two or three <date>o'clock</date> in the <date>morning</date>; at which time I took a melancholy leave of <persName>signor Grimani</persName>, who had honoured <persName>me</persName> with something more than mere politeness and <placeName>hospitality</placeName>: in a less elevated character I should venture to call it friendship, but here it could only be condescending goodness.
To To finish my account of the music of this <placeName>charming <placeName>city</placeName></placeName>, I must observe, that though the <persName>composers</persName> of the <placeName><placeName>Venetian</placeName> <placeName>school</placeName></placeName> are in general good contrapuntists, yet their chief characteristics are delicacy of taste, and fertility of invention; but many circumstances concur to render the music of <placeName>Venice</placeName> better, and more general than elsewhere.
The <persName>Venetians</persName> have few amusements but what the theatres afford; walking, riding, and all fieldsports, are denied them.
This in some degree accounts for music being so much, and in so costly a manner, cultivated; the number too of theatres, in all which the <placeName>Gondoliers</placeName> have admission gratis, may account for the superior manner in which they sing compared with <persName>people</persName> of the same class elsewhere *.
And in the <placeName>private</placeName> families, into which the <persName>girls</persName> of * When a <instrument>box</instrument> belonging to a <persName>noble</persName> family is disengaged, and likely to remain empty, the <instrument>opera</instrument> manager permits the Gondolieri to occupy it, rather than a report should prevail that the performance drew but little <persName>company</persName>.
the the <placeName>Conservatorios</placeName> marry, it is natural to suppose that good taste and a love for music are introduced.
The <placeName>library of <date>st</date></placeName>.
<persName>Mark</persName> here, which abounds with books in all other faculties, afforded <persName>me</persName> but few materials on the subject of music.
However I gained considerably by the conversation of <persName>signor Zanetti</persName>, the first <persName>librarian</persName>, who was very polite and communicative.
Printing has been carried on in <placeName>Venice</placeName> with great spirit, ever since the <date>year</date> <persName>1459</persName>, when it was established there by <persName>Nicholas Jansen</persName>; and there is perhaps no <placeName>city</placeName> in <placeName>Italy</placeName> in which so many books have been published.
At present the press is very active and fertile, and the number of <persName>booksellers</persName> in the fine <placeName>street</placeName> called <persName>Merceria</persName> is very considerable.
I found in no one place so many old <persName>authors</persName> on the subject of music as here; and as to the new, I met with many that I was unable to find elsewhere, particularly the first volume of <persName>Padre Martini</persName> s History I <placeName>History of Music</placeName>.
The principal <persName>booksellers</persName> in <placeName>Venice</placeName> are <persName>Pasquali</persName>, <persName>Remondini</persName>, <persName>Bettinelli</persName>, Occhi, and <placeName>Antonio di Castro</placeName>.
The art of engraving music there seems to be utterly lost, as I was not able to find a single work printed in the manner we print music in <placeName>England</placeName>.
In the first place there is no such thing as a music <persName>shop</persName> throughout <placeName>Italy</placeName>, that I was able to discover.
Indeed <persName>M.
di Castro</persName>, a spirited <persName>bookseller</persName>, one of the four abovementioned, has published a proposal for printing music with types, in the manner attempted by Mr.
Fought, but has met with small encouragement, having only published one book of little <music>duets</music> and <persName>trios</persName>.
Musical compositions are so shortlived in <placeName>Italy</placeName>, such is the rage for novelty, that for the sew copies wanted, it is not worth while to be at the expence of engraving, and of the <persName>rolling-</persName>press.
Indeed there, as in <placeName>Turkey</placeName>, the business of a transcriber furnishes employment for so many <persName>people</persName>, that it is cruel to wish to rob them of it, especially as that trade trade seems more brisk and profitable than any other.
As a supplement to the <placeName>article <placeName>Venice</placeName></placeName>, I must add, that, since my return to <placeName>England</placeName>, I have been favoured with a <persName>letter</persName> from thence, dated <date>January 25</date>, 1771, containing the following particulars relative to the state of music there, at that time.
* At the theatre <music>of s.
Benetto</music> we * have had represented, during the pre“ sent carnival, the <placeName><instrument>opera</instrument> of Alexander</placeName> “ in <placeName>India</placeName>; composed by <persName>signor <persName>Bertoni</persName></persName>, “ <persName>master</persName> of the <placeName>Mendicanti</placeName>, which has *been universally applauded; particu“ <persName>Jarly</persName> a <persName>duet</persName>, sung by signora <persName>de Amicis</persName> c and <persName>signor Caselli</persName>.
At the same “ theatre we have at present il siroe ri- * <music>conosciuto</music>, composed by signor <persName>Borghi</persName>, * which is generally disliked.
* The music, at the <placeName><instrument>opera</instrument>-<placeName>house</placeName> of</placeName> s.
* <persName>Moisè</persName>, pleases very much; notwith“ standing it is so ill executed, that the “ <persName>author</persName>, signor <placeName>Garzaniga</placeName>, a <instrument>Neapoli</instrument>“ tan, has great reason to be mortified, “ though crowned with general praise.
<persName>BOLOGNA</persName>. </body>