{"classes": ["DATE","LOCATION", "PERSON","INSTRUMENT","MUSIC"],
    "annotations":[
    
    [
        "Signor Buranello has preserved all his fire and imagination from the chill blasts of Russia, whence he is lately returned*.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    0,
                    16,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    85,
                    91,
                    "LOCATION"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "He is an able mathematician, a composer, and performer.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    14,
                    27,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    31,
                    39,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    45,
                    54,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "In consequence of a message from Mr. Richie, Chargé des Affaires to his Britannic Majesty, to whom Sir James Wright had honoured me with a letter, and who  very politely and kindly was pleased to interest himself effectually in my service, I was this afternoon favoured with a visit from Signor Latilla, an eminent composer here, and had a long conversation with him relative to the subject of my journey.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    33,
                    43,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    45,
                    64,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    68,
                    89,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    99,
                    115,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    251,
                    260,
                    "DATE"
                ],
                [
                    288,
                    302,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    315,
                    323,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "The people here, at this season, seem to begin to live only at midnight.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    4,
                    10,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    63,
                    71,
                    "DATE"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    
    [
        "Wednesday 8.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    0,
                    11,
                    "DATE"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "In the overture, which was full of pretty * Signor Galuppi is best known in Italy by the name of Buranello, which he acquired from having been born in the little island of Burano, near Venice.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    7,
                    15,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    44,
                    58,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    76,
                    81,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    97,
                    106,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    162,
                    178,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    185,
                    191,
                    "LOCATION"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "The service is performed in the Greek language; the epistles and gospels are chanted by a high-priest in a pulpit, and the prayers and responses are sung in a kind of melody totally different from any other I had ever heard in or out of the church.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    4,
                    11,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    52,
                    60,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    65,
                    72,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    90,
                    101,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    107,
                    113,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    123,
                    130,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    135,
                    144,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    241,
                    247,
                    "LOCATION"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "Venice has likewise been one of the first cities in Europe that has cultivated the musical drama or opera: and, in the graver stile, it has been honoured with a Lotti and a  Marcello.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    0,
                    6,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    52,
                    58,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    83,
                    96,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    100,
                    105,
                    "MUSIC"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "Even after this, upon the Piazza di S. Marco, I heard a great number of vagrant musicians, some in bands, accompanying one or two voices; sometimes a single voice and guitar; and sometimes  or three guitars together.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    26,
                    44,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    72,
                    89,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    99,
                    104,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    130,
                    136,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    157,
                    162,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    167,
                    173,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    199,
                    206,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "The composition and performance I heard to-night did not exceed mediocrity; among the singers I could discover no remarkable fine voice, or performer possessed of great taste.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    40,
                    48,
                    "DATE"
                ],
                [
                    86,
                    93,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    130,
                    135,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    140,
                    149,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "The organist here very judicioussy suffered the voices to be heard in all their purity, in146 somuch that I frequently forgot that they were accompanied; upon the whole this seems to be the true stile for the church: it calls to memory nothing vulgar, light, or prophane; it disposes the mind to philanthrophy, and divests it of its gross and sensual passions.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    4,
                    12,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    48,
                    54,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    209,
                    215,
                    "LOCATION"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "Tuesday 7.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    0,
                    9,
                    "DATE"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    
    [
        "He had travelled into Grecce, in order to make observations in geography, agriculture, and natural history, but being unable to satisfy himself as he expected, his pride was so hurt by the disappointment, that he would not publish any of his remarks or discoveries.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    22,
                    28,
                    "LOCATION"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "However, the instruments finished with a symphony, the first movement of which, in point of spirit, was well written and executed.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    41,
                    49,
                    "MUSIC"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "This music, which was of the higher sort of theatric stile, though it was performed in a church, was not mixed with the church service, and the audience sat the whole time as at a concert; and, indeed, this  might be called a concerto spirituale with great propriety.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    89,
                    95,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    120,
                    134,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    180,
                    187,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    226,
                    245,
                    "MUSIC"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "Indeed it is not to be wondered at, that the streetmusic here is generally neglected, as people are almost stunned with it at every corner; but, however, in justice to the taste and discernment of the Italians, it must be allowed, that when they do admire, it is something excellent; and then; they never \"damn with faint praise\", but express rapture in a manner peculiar to themselves; they seem to agonize with pleasure too great for the aching sense.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    45,
                    56,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    132,
                    138,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    201,
                    209,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "This city is famous for its conservatorios or musical schools, of which it has four, the Ospidale della Pietà, the Mendicanti, the Incurabile, and the Ospidalette a S. Giovanni e Paulo, at each of which there is a performance every Saturday and Sunday evening, as well as on great festivals.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    5,
                    9,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    28,
                    42,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    46,
                    61,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    89,
                    109,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    115,
                    125,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    131,
                    141,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    151,
                    184,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    226,
                    240,
                    "DATE"
                ],
                [
                    245,
                    259,
                    "DATE"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "Several of them had uncommon talents for singing, particularly the Rota, Pasqua Rossi, and the Ortolani; the two last sung the Canticle in dialogue.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    67,
                    71,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    73,
                    85,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    95,
                    103,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    127,
                    135,
                    "MUSIC"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "The words were taken from three or four of the Psalms in Latin, from the hymn Salve Regina, and one of the Canticles put into Latin verse, and in dialogue.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    47,
                    62,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    73,
                    77,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    78,
                    90,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    107,
                    116,
                    "MUSIC"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "Signor Bertoni is the present Maestro di Capella.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    0,
                    14,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    30,
                    48,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "He is a great admirer of the works of Marcello, and sings by heart all his cantatas and best melodies.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    14,
                    21,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    29,
                    46,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    75,
                    83,
                    "MUSIC"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "There was music this evening at the church of St. Laurence, composed and directed by Signor Sacchini, at which, as it was the vigil of this saint, there was a great crowd.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    21,
                    28,
                    "DATE"
                ],
                [
                    36,
                    58,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    85,
                    100,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    165,
                    170,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    
    [
        "These girls are maintained here till they are  married, and all those who have talents for music are taught by the best masters of Italy.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    6,
                    11,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    120,
                    127,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    131,
                    136,
                    "LOCATION"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    
    [
        "This morning there was a mass in music at the church of S. Gaetano.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    5,
                    12,
                    "DATE"
                ],
                [
                    25,
                    29,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    46,
                    66,
                    "LOCATION"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "This day was remark- able for no enquiry relative to the present state of music in Italy; however it  deserves mention here, on account of the opportunity it afforded me of conversing with the Abate Martini, one of the best judges of every part of music, ancient and modern, that I had yet met with.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    83,
                    88,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    193,
                    206,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    224,
                    230,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "The able master was discoverable in all the cadences of these young subjects.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    9,
                    15,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    68,
                    76,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "I had many enquiries to make, and had very sanguine expectations from this city, with regard to the music of past times as well as the present.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    75,
                    79,
                    "LOCATION"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "It being a great festival, all the treasures and relics were exposed to public view, and there was a very great crowd.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    112,
                    117,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "Luckily for me, this night, a barge, in which there was an excellent band of music, consisting of violins, flutes, horns, bases, and a kettle-drum, with a pretty good tenor voice, was on the great canal, and stopped very near the house where I lodged; it was a piece of gallantry, at the expence of an inamorato in order to senerade his mistress.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    30,
                    35,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    69,
                    82,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    98,
                    105,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    107,
                    113,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    115,
                    120,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    122,
                    127,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    135,
                    146,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    173,
                    178,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    191,
                    202,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    230,
                    235,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    261,
                    279,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    302,
                    311,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    337,
                    345,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "Shakespeare says of nocturnal music, \"Methinks it sounds much sweeter than by day.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    0,
                    11,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    20,
                    35,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    78,
                    81,
                    "DATE"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "Monday 6.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    0,
                    8,
                    "DATE"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "He is uncle to Signor Piccini.   overture, and part of the first air.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    15,
                    30,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    33,
                    41,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    65,
                    68,
                    "MUSIC"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "The voices were not good enough sor long solo parts, nor strong enough to get through a large band; however there were many very pleasing and agreeable movements, and some of the chorusses ",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    4,
                    10,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    41,
                    51,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    94,
                    98,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    152,
                    161,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    179,
                    188,
                    "MUSIC"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "The Abate has, however, collected a set of apophthegms or  proverbs, which he intends to publish, and which will discover the manners and misery of the modern Greeks, perhaps more effectually than any other work could do.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    4,
                    9,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    159,
                    165,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "The present Maestro di Capella is Signor Furlanetti, a priest, and the performers, both vocal and instrumental, are all girls; the organ, violins, flutes, violoncellos, and even French horns, are supplied by these females.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    12,
                    30,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    34,
                    51,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    55,
                    61,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    71,
                    81,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    120,
                    125,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    131,
                    136,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    138,
                    145,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    147,
                    153,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    155,
                    167,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    178,
                    190,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    214,
                    221,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "I admired his candour in advising me to go to the Incurabili, to hear the girls perform there, with whom he said I should be much pleased.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    50,
                    60,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    74,
                    79,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "On Sunday morning, August 5, I went to the Greek church, which has been tolerated here ever since the time of Leo X.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    3,
                    27,
                    "DATE"
                ],
                [
                    43,
                    55,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    110,
                    115,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "They are scholars of Signor Galuppi, who is Maestro di Capella of this Conservatorio.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    9,
                    17,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    21,
                    35,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    44,
                    62,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    71,
                    84,
                    "LOCATION"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "This morning the Doge went in procession to the church of S. Giovanni e Paolo.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    5,
                    12,
                    "DATE"
                ],
                [
                    17,
                    21,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    48,
                    77,
                    "LOCATION"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "In short, I was extremely entertained by this performance, and the whole company, which was very nu- merous, seemed equally pleased.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    73,
                    80,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "The voices were well chosen, and well assorted, no one stronger than the other; the composition was of Signor Lotti, and was truly grave and majestic, consisting of fugues and imitations in the stile of our best old church services, which have been so well selected, and published in so magnificent a manner by Dr. Boyce; all was clear and distinct, no confusion or unnecessary notes; it was even capable of expression, particularly one of the movements, into which the performers entered so well, that it affected me even to tears.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    4,
                    10,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    103,
                    115,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    165,
                    171,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    176,
                    186,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    216,
                    231,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    311,
                    320,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    470,
                    480,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "9th.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    0,
                    3,
                    "DATE"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "The performers here too are all orphan girls; one of them, la Ferrarese, sung very well, and had a very extraordinary compass of voice, as she was able to reach the highest E of our harpsichords, upon which she could dwell a considerable time, in a fair, natural voice.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    4,
                    14,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    32,
                    44,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    59,
                    71,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    129,
                    134,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    182,
                    194,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    263,
                    268,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "They did such things in that way, especially the Rota, as I do not remember to have heard attempted before.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    49,
                    53,
                    "MUSIC"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "Then the canals are crowded with gondolas, and St. Mark's square with company; the banks too of the canals are all peopled, and harmony prevails in every part.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    9,
                    15,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    47,
                    64,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    83,
                    88,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    100,
                    106,
                    "LOCATION"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "VENICE.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    0,
                    6,
                    "LOCATION"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "The first music I heard here was in the street, immediately on my arrival, performed by an itinerant band of two fiddles, a violoncello, and a voice, who, though as unnoticed here as small-coalmen or oyster-women in England, performed so well, that in any other country of Europe they would not only have excited attention, but have acquired applause, which they justly merited.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    40,
                    46,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    91,
                    105,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    113,
                    120,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    124,
                    135,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    143,
                    148,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    183,
                    196,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    200,
                    212,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    216,
                    223,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    262,
                    269,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    273,
                    279,
                    "LOCATION"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "These two violins played difficult passages very neatly, the base stopped well in tune, and the voice, which was a woman's, was well toned, and had several essentials belonging to that of a good singer, such as compass, shake, and volubility; but I ſhall not mention all the performances of this kind  kind which I met with here; as they happened so frequently, the repetition would be tiresome.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    10,
                    17,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    96,
                    101,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    115,
                    120,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    195,
                    201,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "In the afternoon of the same day I went to the hospital de Mendicanti, for orphan girls, who are taught to sing and play, and on Sundays and festivals they sing divine service in chorus.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    7,
                    16,
                    "DATE"
                ],
                [
                    29,
                    32,
                    "DATE"
                ],
                [
                    47,
                    69,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    75,
                    87,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    129,
                    136,
                    "DATE"
                ],
                [
                    141,
                    150,
                    "DATE"
                ],
                [
                    161,
                    175,
                    "MUSIC"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "At St. Luke's church I likewise heard part of a mass with instruments; some of the tenor voices here were good, and the airs written and sung with taste; the music was composed by a priest.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    3,
                    20,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    48,
                    52,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    89,
                    95,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    120,
                    124,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    182,
                    188,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    
    [
        "The subjects of the fugues and chorusses were trite, and but slightly put together.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    20,
                    26,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    31,
                    40,
                    "MUSIC"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "The composer of the music, and the person who beat the time was Signor Menagatto, a priest; I cannot say that I received much pleasure from this performance, the organ was coarse, and poorly played; the voices only two indifferent tenors, and a base, and the composition very common, and unmarked by any stamp of original genius.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    4,
                    12,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    64,
                    80,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    84,
                    90,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    162,
                    167,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    203,
                    209,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    245,
                    249,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "There was an excellent fugue in the last chorus, well worked and well performed.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    23,
                    28,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    41,
                    47,
                    "MUSIC"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    
    [
        "I had this afternoon another long conversation with the same learned gentleman, who was so obliging as to bring his manuscript papers concerning Greek music, and to desire my acceptance of them.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    11,
                    20,
                    "DATE"
                ],
                [
                    69,
                    78,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "One of the organists of St. Mark's church, who is in orders, attended, and discovered himself, in his voluntaries and interludes, to be a very masterly performer.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    11,
                    20,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    24,
                    41,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    152,
                    161,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "In this there is no organ, but it is more crowded with ornaments, and its ceremonials are more numerous than in any of the Romish churches.   From thence I went to St. Marc’s, and heard a mass in music, which was sung by the priests, accompanied by the organ only, much in the manner of our full anthems.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    20,
                    25,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    123,
                    139,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    164,
                    174,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    188,
                    192,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    225,
                    232,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    253,
                    258,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    296,
                    303,
                    "MUSIC"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "The young singers, just mentioned, are absolute nightingales; they have a facility of executing difficult divisions equal to that of birds.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    10,
                    17,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "Add to these advantages the conservatorios established here, and the songs of the Gondolieri, or Water-men, which are so celebrated, that every musical collector of taste in Europe is well furnished with them, and it will appear that my expectations were well grounded.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    28,
                    42,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    69,
                    92,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    97,
                    106,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    152,
                    161,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    174,
                    180,
                    "LOCATION"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "Silence bestows the virtue on it—I think The nightingale, if she should sing by day, When every goose is cackling, would be thought No better a musician than the wren.\" Whether the time, place, and manner of performing this music, gave it adventitious and collateral charms, I will not pretend to say; all I know is, that the  symphonies seemed to me to be admirable, full of fancy, full of fire; the passages well contrasted; sometimes the graceful, sometimes the pathetic prevailed; and sometimes, however strange it may be thought, even noise and fury had their effect.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    144,
                    152,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "Unluckily when I arrived there, the performance was begun, however, I had only lost the * Most of the comic operas performed in London with such success, in the time of Pertici and Laschi, were of Latilla's composition; particularly La Comedia in Comedia, Don Calascione, and others.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    102,
                    114,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    128,
                    134,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    169,
                    176,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    181,
                    187,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    197,
                    204,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    233,
                    254,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    256,
                    270,
                    "MUSIC"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "It is a kind of Foundling Hospital for natural children, under the protection of several nobles, citizens, and merchants, who, though the revenue is very great, yet contribute annually to its support.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    16,
                    34,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    47,
                    55,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    89,
                    95,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    97,
                    105,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    111,
                    120,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "They had here, last Carnival, seven opera-houses open at once, three serious, and four comic, besides four play-houses, and these were all crowded every night.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    15,
                    28,
                    "DATE"
                ],
                [
                    36,
                    48,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    107,
                    118,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    147,
                    158,
                    "DATE"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "I suffered, as well as every one else, too much by the heat, perhaps, to be easily pleased, and the composition seemed rather more common than that I had heard of this ingenious master before; however, the vocal parts were not so well performed, as there were no other singers than those of St. Mark's church, who most excel in mere church music, accompanied only by the organ.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    178,
                    184,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    269,
                    276,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    291,
                    308,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    333,
                    345,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    371,
                    376,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    
    [
        "Among other curious enquires, he made many concerning the music of the modern Greeks, in hopes it would throw some light upon that of the ancient.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    78,
                    84,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    
    [
        "The girls here I thought accompanied the voices better than at the Pietà: as the chorusses are wholly made up of female voices, they are never in more than three parts, often only in two; but these, when reinforced by the instruments, have such an effect, that the full complement to the chords is not missed, and the melody is much more sensible and marked, by being less charged with harmony.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    4,
                    9,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    67,
                    72,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    81,
                    90,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    113,
                    126,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "The overture, and the whole of this last performance were for two orchestras.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    4,
                    12,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    66,
                    76,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "I could not help regarding this present as a valuable acquisition, for though the materials it contained were too few for his original purpose of forming a booi, they appeared likely to be of importance in the course of a work, in which it is proposed to treat not only of ancient music, but of the national music of most parts of the world, from whence specimens, or accounts well authenticated can be had.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    273,
                    286,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    299,
                    313,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    335,
                    340,
                    "LOCATION"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ]
]}