{"classes": ["DATE","LOCATION", "PERSON","INSTRUMENT","MUSIC"],
    "annotations":[
    [
        "He was so obliging as to play several of his master's solos, particularly two which he had made just before his death, of which I begged a copy, regarding these last drops of his pen as sacred relics of so great and original a genius.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    54,
                    59,
                    "MUSIC"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "I found him to be a plain, sensible man, of about sixty years of age, who had both read and thought much concerning the music of the ancients, as well as that of the moderns, to which he has contributed a considerable share for many years past*.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    36,
                    39,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    120,
                    141,
                    "MUSIC"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "Upon the whole, there seemed to be as much genius in this composition as in any I had heard since my arrival in Italy.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    112,
                    117,
                    "LOCATION"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "I was not only curious to see this procession, but to hear the music, which I expected would be very considerable, and by a great band; however there was only a mass sung in four  parts, without other instrument than the organ, but then it was so good of the kind, so well executed and accompanied, that I do not remember to have received more pleasure from such music.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    130,
                    134,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    161,
                    165,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    221,
                    226,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "Indeed my being moved was the mere effect of well-modulated and well-measured sounds, for I knew not the words, which were wholly lost by the distance; nor is this species of music at all favourable to poetry: in the answers that are made to the points, the several parts all sing different words, so that no great effects can be produced by them; but notwithstanding this defect, such music as this, in the service of the church, must ever be allowed to have its merit, however it may be exploded, or unfit for theatrical purposes.",
        {
            "entities": []
        }
    ],
    [
        "This ingenious, entertaining, and elegant composer abounds in novelty, in spirit, and in delicacy, and his scholars did his music great justice.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    107,
                    115,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "From hence I went to the Ospidaletto, of which Signor Sacchini is the master, and was indeed very much pleased by the composition of part of the famous hymn Salve Regina, which was singing when I entered the church; it was new, spirited, and full of ingenious contrivances for the instruments, which always said something interesting without disturbing the voice.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    25,
                    36,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    47,
                    62,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    70,
                    76,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    152,
                    156,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    157,
                    169,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    208,
                    214,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    357,
                    362,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "If two of the common people walk together arm in arm, they seem to converse  in song; if there is company on the water, in a gondola, it is the same; a mere melody, unaccompanied with a second part, is not to be heard in this city: all the ballads in the streets are sung in duo.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    14,
                    27,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    113,
                    118,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    125,
                    132,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    226,
                    230,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    240,
                    247,
                    "MUSIC"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "The instrumental parts were very well executed, and the whole indicated a superior genius in the composer and conductor of the performance.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    97,
                    105,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    110,
                    119,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "The church of St. Marc has had a constant supply of able masters, from the time of Adriano, Zarlino's predecessor, to Galuppi, its present worthy composer.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    4,
                    22,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    57,
                    64,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    83,
                    90,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    92,
                    99,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    102,
                    113,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    118,
                    125,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    146,
                    154,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "I went to that of the Pietà, the evening after my arrival, Saturday, August 4.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    22,
                    27,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    33,
                    40,
                    "DATE"
                ],
                [
                    59,
                    77,
                    "DATE"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    
    [
        "The day before my departure from Padua, I visited Signor Tromba, Tartini's scholar and successor.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    4,
                    7,
                    "DATE"
                ],
                [
                    33,
                    38,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    50,
                    63,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    65,
                    72,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    75,
                    82,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    87,
                    96,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "There was a hymn performed with solos and chorusses, and a mottetto à voce sola, which last was very well performed, particularly an accompanied recitative, which was pronounced with great force and energy.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    12,
                    16,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    32,
                    37,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    42,
                    51,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    59,
                    79,
                    "MUSIC"
                ],
                [
                    145,
                    155,
                    "MUSIC"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "If, for instance, the five sounds c. d. e. f. g, are all struck at the same instant on the harpsichord, provided the d and the f are taken soon off, and the three others remain, the ear will not suffer much by the first shock.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    91,
                    102,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "He is replaced at Petersburg by Signor Traetta.  passages, the two bands echoed each other.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    18,
                    28,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    32,
                    47,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    67,
                    72,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "He knows, I believe, as much as any one else, about the systems of Pythagoras, Ptolemy, and the writers collected by Meibomius, as well as of Rameau and Tartini.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    67,
                    77,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    79,
                    86,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    96,
                    103,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    117,
                    126,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    142,
                    148,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    153,
                    160,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "In these hospitals many of the girls sing in the counter tenor as low as A and G, which enables them always to keep below the soprano and mezzo soprano, to which they sing the base; and this seems to have been long practised in Italy, as may be seen in the examples of composition given in the old writers, such as Zarlino, Glariano, Kircher, and others, where the lowest part of three is often written in the counter-tenor clef.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    9,
                    18,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    31,
                    36,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    228,
                    233,
                    "LOCATION"
                ],
                [
                    294,
                    305,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    315,
                    322,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    324,
                    332,
                    "PERSON"
                ],
                [
                    334,
                    341,
                    "PERSON"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ],
    [
        "There were two organs, and two pair of French horns.",
        {
            "entities": [
                [
                    15,
                    21,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ],
                [
                    39,
                    51,
                    "INSTRUMENT"
                ]
            ]
        }
    ]
]}